<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: learning | PsiQED]]></title>
  <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/blog/categories/learning/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-06T21:01:44-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://npisenti.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Neal Pisenti]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Quals: Studying Strategy?]]></title>
    <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2013/01/the-quals-studying-strategy/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-05T11:58:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2013/01/the-quals-studying-strategy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The physics qualifier exam is a week from next Thursday. There is definitely a lot of material one needs to know. Here is a breif outline of how I plan to attack the studying.</p>

<h3>Use the "Feynman Technique"</h3>

<p>The basic idea behind the <a href="http://www.scotthyoung.com/learnonsteroids/learnfast.html">Feynman Technique</a> is to understand a complex idea by explaining it in simple language.
Scott Young sketches four steps:</p>

<ol>
<li>Pick your topic</li>
<li>Explain it as if you were talking to a novice (kinda like Cal Newport's <a href="http://calnewport.com/blog/2012/08/10/you-know-what-you-write-the-textbook-method-for-ultra-learning">textbook method</a>)</li>
<li>If you get stuck, go back to the book</li>
<li>Simplify, synthesize, and create analogies</li>
</ol>


<h3>Section summaries</h3>

<p>I haven't done (really any) E&amp;M for almost two years now. I'm planning to read through Griffith's E&amp;M textbook, and apply the Feynman technique on
sections I'm not fully comfortable with.</p>

<h3>Problems, problems, problems...</h3>

<p>There are qualifier problems <a href="http://umdphysics.umd.edu/academics/graduate/qualifier.html">online</a> from tests dating back to 2005, and in printed form dating back into the late eighties (?!). I'm going to do as many of these as possible, starting with the most recent exams.</p>

<h3>Top-heavy studying</h3>

<p>Again, hat tip to <a href="http://www.scotthyoung.com/learnonsteroids/getmoredone.html">Scott Young</a>. The idea here is to front-load your days with work, doing more in the morning
and less in the afternoon/evening. This supposedly helps focus, and prevents burnout. He also suggests structuring your weeks like this too, although with such a short amount
of time left, not sure I can afford to take any days off...</p>

<p>At any rate, here's to a good show! I'll try a post-game analysis to see how well everything worked for me. I'm also planning a post about an idea I've been toying with
on how to integrate both tablet and computer for enhanced note taking, à la personal study wikis/the textbook method.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
