<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: physics | PsiQED]]></title>
  <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/blog/categories/physics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-30T12:58:28-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://npisenti.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Neal Pisenti]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Motivating the Lagrangian]]></title>
    <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2013/03/motivating-the-euler-lagrange-equations/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-30T17:09:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2013/03/motivating-the-euler-lagrange-equations</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the coolest things about physics is that physical laws can be formulated
in many different ways! It’s mindblowing to me that the universe has some
underlying mathematical structure which makes this the case…</p>

<p>For example, take Newtonian mechanics. We’re all familiar with Newton’s second
law from high school:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display"> F = m\ddot x</script>

<p>Later, if you take a course in theoretical mechanics, you discover that
mechanics can be re-cast in the so-called “Lagrangian Formalism” – that is, if
we define some quantity called the <em>Lagrangian</em></p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display"> L = T - V </script>

<p>(where <script type="math/tex">T</script> is the kinetic energy, and <script type="math/tex">V</script> is the potential energy), then
objects follow trajectories calculated from the Euler-Lagrange differential
equation </p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display"> \frac{d}{dt}\left(\frac{\partial L}{\partial \dot x}\right) - \frac{\partial
L}{\partial x} = 0 </script>

<p>Solving for <script type="math/tex">x(t)</script> gives you paths which minimize some theoretical construct
<script type="math/tex">S = \int L dt</script> called the <strong>action.</strong> We can derive the Euler-Lagrange
equation using the calculus of variations, basically by demanding that any
deviation from our object’s trajectory <script type="math/tex">x(t)</script> will increase <script type="math/tex">S</script>.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>  </p>

<p>Or, to strip out the physics jargon, it simply means that *objects in classical
mechanics move in such a way that they minimize the difference between their
kinetic and potential energies.**</p>

<p>Why do we care about this alternative formulation of classical mechanics? After
all, the Euler-Lagrange equation looks a lot more complicated than Newton’s
<script type="math/tex">F=ma</script>…</p>

<p>Besides the obvious answer, “Because it’s cool!”, it’s worth pointing out that
the two formulations essentially answer different questions. Newton’s second law
(which, by the way, is also a differential equation in desguise!) is answering
the question, “I see this object at point A moving with velocity <script type="math/tex">v</script>; what is
its trajectory?” In other words, solving Newton’s equation requires a position
and a velocity as initial condition.</p>

<p>In Lagrangian mechanics, we are asking a (slightly) different question: “What
path does an object take between points A &amp; B?” That is to say, our initial
conditions specify two points along a trajectory, and we want to fill in the
rest. Many problems which are completely intractable to solve with <script type="math/tex">F=ma</script>
become easy in this formalism; again, that’s what makes physics so damn cool! </p>

<h2 id="why-is-the-lagrangian-kinetic-minus-potential-energy">Why is the Lagrangian Kinetic minus Potential Energy?</h2>

<p>I’ve always been slightly bothered by the ad-hoc form of the Lagrangian. The
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principle_of_least_action">Principle of Least
Action</a> at least makes
heuristic sense to me, but why should nature choose to minimize the integral of
kinetic <em>minus</em> potential energy along a given path? Why not minimize some other
quantity?</p>

<p>Remarkably, we can derive the Euler-Lagrange equations in a different
way, starting from Newton’s laws and completely avoiding the calculus of
variations. This method illuminates why <script type="math/tex">L = T-V</script>.</p>

<p>Lagrange’s crucial insight was to use <em>functionals</em> (that is, functions of
functions) of the form </p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display"> f \rightarrow f[x(t), \dot x(t), t] </script>

<p>where we parametrize our trajectory <script type="math/tex">x(t)</script> by time, <script type="math/tex">t</script>, but also allow the
time derivative <script type="math/tex">\dot x = \partial x/\partial t</script> to enter in as an independent
variable! (No clue if this was Lagrange’s actual thought process, but I’ll give
him the credit anyways.)</p>

<p>Now, we take Newton’s second law (where the force is writen as the negative
gradient of potential energy)</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display"> F = -\frac{\partial V}{\partial x} = m \frac{d}{dt}\dot x </script>

<p>Since <script type="math/tex">\dot x</script> is being treated as it’s own independent variable, we can
re-write <script type="math/tex">\dot x</script> as</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display"> \dot x = \frac{\partial}{\partial \dot x}\left(\frac{1}{2}\dot x^2\right)_{x,t} </script>

<p>subbing this in, we get</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display"> - \frac{\partial V}{\partial x} = \frac{d}{dt}\frac{\partial}{\partial \dot
x}\left(\frac{1}{2}m\dot x^2\right) </script>

<p>Considering potentials <script type="math/tex">V \rightarrow V(x,t)</script> which do not depend on
<script type="math/tex">\dot x</script><sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, we can re-write the left-hand side like</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">-\frac{\partial V}{\partial x} = \frac{\partial}{\partial x}\left(
\frac{1}{2}m \dot x^2 - V \right) </script>

<p>Putting it all together, we get</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
\frac{\partial}{\partial x}\left(\frac{1}{2}m \dot x^2 - V\right) =
\frac{d}{dt}\frac{\partial}{\partial \dot x}\left(\frac{1}{2}m \dot x^2 -
V\right)</script>

<p>Now, let’s call the quantity</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display"> L = \frac{1}{2}m \dot x^2 - V </script>

<p>the “Lagrangian,” and we see that we arrive at the exact same result as we did
using the Principle of Least action! </p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display"> \frac{d}{dt}\left(\frac{\partial L}{\partial \dot x}\right) = \frac{\partial
L}{\partial x} </script>

<p>Wicked.</p>

<hr />

<p>h/t to <a href="http://terpconnect.umd.edu/~hassam/">Professor Hassam</a> for the
ideas in this derivation!</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>I guess if we are being careful, it means objects follow paths for which the action is an extrema – either a maximum or a minimum.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>I realize this argument doesn’t work for things like the magnetic force which are velocity dependent, which makes it even more remarkable that the traditional calculus of variations approach does!<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
