<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[PsiQED]]></title>
  <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-06T21:00:42-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://npisenti.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Neal Pisenti]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A few new year's resolutions]]></title>
    <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2013/01/a-few-new-years-resolutions/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-06T20:48:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2013/01/a-few-new-years-resolutions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just gonna put them out there:</p>

<ul>
<li>Exercise more. I am looking at bikes on Craigslist, and am shooting for a stationary setup in our attic (w/ ubuntu box for netflix&#8230;). I also want to hack an arduino to record and track workout statistics.</li>
<li>Actually write this blog. Let&#8217;s say 3 posts a week; might take a while to get warmed up however.</li>
<li>Do a better job <em>studying</em> physics. I could be doing much more with material from my classes.</li>
<li>Spin off some project ideas into something real and useable (ie, outside my imagination). Maybe try to turn one of them into something people would buy.</li>
<li>Have fun!</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Quals: Studying Strategy?]]></title>
    <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2013/01/the-quals-studying-strategy/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-05T11:58:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2013/01/the-quals-studying-strategy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The physics qualifier exam is a week from next Thursday. There is definitely a lot of material one needs to know. Here is a breif outline of how I plan to attack the studying.</p>

<h3>Use the &#8220;Feynman Technique&#8221;</h3>

<p>The basic idea behind the <a href="http://www.scotthyoung.com/learnonsteroids/learnfast.html">Feynman Technique</a> is to understand a complex idea by explaining it in simple language.
Scott Young sketches four steps:</p>

<ol>
<li>Pick your topic</li>
<li>Explain it as if you were talking to a novice (kinda like Cal Newport&#8217;s <a href="http://calnewport.com/blog/2012/08/10/you-know-what-you-write-the-textbook-method-for-ultra-learning">textbook method</a>)</li>
<li>If you get stuck, go back to the book</li>
<li>Simplify, synthesize, and create analogies</li>
</ol>


<h3>Section summaries</h3>

<p>I haven&#8217;t done (really any) E&amp;M for almost two years now. I&#8217;m planning to read through Griffith&#8217;s E&amp;M textbook, and apply the Feynman technique on
sections I&#8217;m not fully comfortable with.</p>

<h3>Problems, problems, problems&#8230;</h3>

<p>There are qualifier problems <a href="http://umdphysics.umd.edu/academics/graduate/qualifier.html">online</a> from tests dating back to 2005, and in printed form dating back into the late eighties (?!). I&#8217;m going to do as many of these as possible, starting with the most recent exams.</p>

<h3>Top-heavy studying</h3>

<p>Again, hat tip to <a href="http://www.scotthyoung.com/learnonsteroids/getmoredone.html">Scott Young</a>. The idea here is to front-load your days with work, doing more in the morning
and less in the afternoon/evening. This supposedly helps focus, and prevents burnout. He also suggests structuring your weeks like this too, although with such a short amount
of time left, not sure I can afford to take any days off&#8230;</p>

<p>At any rate, here&#8217;s to a good show! I&#8217;ll try a post-game analysis to see how well everything worked for me. I&#8217;m also planning a post about an idea I&#8217;ve been toying with
on how to integrate both tablet and computer for enhanced note taking, à la personal study wikis/the textbook method.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[EZProxify - UMD libraries proxy for reading articles at home]]></title>
    <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2013/01/ezproxify-umd-libraries-proxy-for-reading-articles-at-home/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-03T23:26:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2013/01/ezproxify-umd-libraries-proxy-for-reading-articles-at-home</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here&#8217;s a cool little bookmarklet you can use to access journal articles while outside of the UMD IP address block:</p>

<p><a href="javascript:void(location.href='http://proxy-um.researchport.umd.edu/login?url='+location.href)">EZProxify</a></p>

<p>Just drag that link to your address bar, and you&#8217;re set to go!
If you find an article you want to read from home, just click the bookmarklet
and you&#8217;ll be routed through the UMD libraries proxy server.</p>

<p>[<a href="http://lib.guides.umd.edu/content.php?pid=233784&amp;sid=1934195">UMD libraries reference page</a>]</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing the (official) launch of PsiQED]]></title>
    <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2012/07/announcing-the-official-launch-of-psiqed/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-02T11:13:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2012/07/announcing-the-official-launch-of-psiqed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The title pretty much says it all &#8211; I&#8217;m finally launching a blog as I segue
into the graduate lifestyle and start <a href="http://umdphysics.umd.edu/">PhD School</a> in August.</p>

<p>I plan to post on a variety of topics (the only real criterion being things that
interests me), but posts will likely cluster around physics, education,
technology, and the occasional (software) hack. I also plan to write
<a href="http://blog.learnstream.org/2012/01/weekly-review-through-december-19/">weekly reviews</a>
to summarize and collect my thoughts on the week, however interesting or mundane they might be.</p>

<p>That&#8217;s about it; stay tuned and check back. We&#8217;ll see if I can actually keep this up.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
