<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[PsiQED]]></title>
  <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-30T23:07:30-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://npisenti.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Neal Pisenti]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Motivating the Lagrangian]]></title>
    <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2013/03/motivating-the-euler-lagrange-equations/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-30T17:09:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2013/03/motivating-the-euler-lagrange-equations</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the coolest things about physics is that physical laws can be formulated
in many different ways! It’s mindblowing to me that the universe has some
underlying mathematical structure which makes this the case…</p>

<p>For example, take Newtonian mechanics. We’re all familiar with Newton’s second
law from high school:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display"> F = m\ddot x</script>

<p>Later, if you take a course in theoretical mechanics, you discover that
mechanics can be re-cast in the so-called “Lagrangian Formalism” – that is, if
we define some quantity called the <em>Lagrangian</em></p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display"> L = T - V </script>

<p>(where <script type="math/tex">T</script> is the kinetic energy, and <script type="math/tex">V</script> is the potential energy), then
objects follow trajectories calculated from the Euler-Lagrange differential
equation </p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display"> \frac{d}{dt}\left(\frac{\partial L}{\partial \dot x}\right) - \frac{\partial
L}{\partial x} = 0 </script>

<p>Solving for <script type="math/tex">x(t)</script> gives you paths which minimize some theoretical construct
<script type="math/tex">S = \int L dt</script> called the <strong>action.</strong> We can derive the Euler-Lagrange
equation using the calculus of variations, basically by demanding that any
deviation from our object’s trajectory <script type="math/tex">x(t)</script> will increase <script type="math/tex">S</script>.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>  </p>

<p>Or, to strip out the physics jargon, it simply means that *objects in classical
mechanics move in such a way that they minimize the difference between their
kinetic and potential energies.**</p>

<p>Why do we care about this alternative formulation of classical mechanics? After
all, the Euler-Lagrange equation looks a lot more complicated than Newton’s
<script type="math/tex">F=ma</script>…</p>

<p>Besides the obvious answer, “Because it’s cool!”, it’s worth pointing out that
the two formulations essentially answer different questions. Newton’s second law
(which, by the way, is also a differential equation in desguise!) is answering
the question, “I see this object at point A moving with velocity <script type="math/tex">v</script>; what is
its trajectory?” In other words, solving Newton’s equation requires a position
and a velocity as initial condition.</p>

<p>In Lagrangian mechanics, we are asking a (slightly) different question: “What
path does an object take between points A &amp; B?” That is to say, our initial
conditions specify two points along a trajectory, and we want to fill in the
rest. Many problems which are completely intractable to solve with <script type="math/tex">F=ma</script>
become easy in this formalism; again, that’s what makes physics so damn cool! </p>

<h2 id="why-is-the-lagrangian-kinetic-minus-potential-energy">Why is the Lagrangian Kinetic minus Potential Energy?</h2>

<p>I’ve always been slightly bothered by the ad-hoc form of the Lagrangian. The
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principle_of_least_action">Principle of Least
Action</a> at least makes
heuristic sense to me, but why should nature choose to minimize the integral of
kinetic <em>minus</em> potential energy along a given path? Why not minimize some other
quantity?</p>

<p>Remarkably, we can derive the Euler-Lagrange equations in a different
way, starting from Newton’s laws and completely avoiding the calculus of
variations. This method illuminates why <script type="math/tex">L = T-V</script>.</p>

<p>Lagrange’s crucial insight was to use <em>functionals</em> (that is, functions of
functions) of the form </p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display"> f \rightarrow f[x(t), \dot x(t), t] </script>

<p>where we parametrize our trajectory <script type="math/tex">x(t)</script> by time, <script type="math/tex">t</script>, but also allow the
time derivative <script type="math/tex">\dot x = \partial x/\partial t</script> to enter in as an independent
variable! (No clue if this was Lagrange’s actual thought process, but I’ll give
him the credit anyways.)</p>

<p>Now, we take Newton’s second law (where the force is writen as the negative
gradient of potential energy)</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display"> F = -\frac{\partial V}{\partial x} = m \frac{d}{dt}\dot x </script>

<p>Since <script type="math/tex">\dot x</script> is being treated as it’s own independent variable, we can
re-write <script type="math/tex">\dot x</script> as</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display"> \dot x = \frac{\partial}{\partial \dot x}\left(\frac{1}{2}\dot x^2\right)_{x,t} </script>

<p>subbing this in, we get</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display"> - \frac{\partial V}{\partial x} = \frac{d}{dt}\frac{\partial}{\partial \dot
x}\left(\frac{1}{2}m\dot x^2\right) </script>

<p>Considering potentials <script type="math/tex">V \rightarrow V(x,t)</script> which do not depend on
<script type="math/tex">\dot x</script><sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, we can re-write the left-hand side like</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">-\frac{\partial V}{\partial x} = \frac{\partial}{\partial x}\left(
\frac{1}{2}m \dot x^2 - V \right) </script>

<p>Putting it all together, we get</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
\frac{\partial}{\partial x}\left(\frac{1}{2}m \dot x^2 - V\right) =
\frac{d}{dt}\frac{\partial}{\partial \dot x}\left(\frac{1}{2}m \dot x^2 -
V\right)</script>

<p>Now, let’s call the quantity</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display"> L = \frac{1}{2}m \dot x^2 - V </script>

<p>the “Lagrangian,” and we see that we arrive at the exact same result as we did
using the Principle of Least action! </p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display"> \frac{d}{dt}\left(\frac{\partial L}{\partial \dot x}\right) = \frac{\partial
L}{\partial x} </script>

<p>Wicked.</p>

<hr />

<p>h/t to <a href="http://terpconnect.umd.edu/~hassam/">Professor Hassam</a> for the
ideas in this derivation!</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>I guess if we are being careful, it means objects follow paths for which the action is an extrema – either a maximum or a minimum.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>I realize this argument doesn’t work for things like the magnetic force which are velocity dependent, which makes it even more remarkable that the traditional calculus of variations approach does!<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A few new year's resolutions]]></title>
    <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2013/01/a-few-new-years-resolutions/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-06T20:48:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2013/01/a-few-new-years-resolutions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just gonna put them out there:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Exercise more. I am looking at bikes on Craigslist, and am shooting for a stationary setup in our attic (w/ ubuntu box for netflix…). I also want to hack an arduino to record and track workout statistics.</li>
  <li>Actually write this blog. Let’s say 3 posts a week; might take a while to get warmed up however.</li>
  <li>Do a better job <em>studying</em> physics. I could be doing much more with material from my classes.</li>
  <li>Spin off some project ideas into something real and useable (ie, outside my imagination). Maybe try to turn one of them into something people would buy.</li>
  <li>Read more. Book suggestions welcome.</li>
  <li>Have fun!</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Quals: Studying Strategy?]]></title>
    <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2013/01/the-quals-studying-strategy/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-05T11:58:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2013/01/the-quals-studying-strategy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The physics qualifier exam is a week from next Thursday. There is definitely a lot of material one needs to know. Here is a breif outline of how I plan to attack the studying.</p>

<h3 id="use-the-feynman-technique">Use the “Feynman Technique”</h3>

<p>The basic idea behind the <a href="http://www.scotthyoung.com/learnonsteroids/learnfast.html">Feynman Technique</a> is to understand a complex idea by explaining it in simple language.
Scott Young sketches four steps:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Pick your topic</li>
  <li>Explain it as if you were talking to a novice (kinda like Cal Newport’s <a href="http://calnewport.com/blog/2012/08/10/you-know-what-you-write-the-textbook-method-for-ultra-learning">textbook method</a>)</li>
  <li>If you get stuck, go back to the book</li>
  <li>Simplify, synthesize, and create analogies </li>
</ol>

<h3 id="section-summaries">Section summaries</h3>

<p>I haven’t done (really any) E&amp;M for almost two years now. I’m planning to read through Griffith’s E&amp;M textbook, and apply the Feynman technique on 
sections I’m not fully comfortable with.</p>

<h3 id="problems-problems-problems">Problems, problems, problems…</h3>

<p>There are qualifier problems <a href="http://umdphysics.umd.edu/academics/graduate/qualifier.html">online</a> from tests dating back to 2005, and in printed form dating back into the late eighties (?!). I’m going to do as many of these as possible, starting with the most recent exams.</p>

<h3 id="top-heavy-studying">Top-heavy studying</h3>

<p>Again, hat tip to <a href="http://www.scotthyoung.com/learnonsteroids/getmoredone.html">Scott Young</a>. The idea here is to front-load your days with work, doing more in the morning
and less in the afternoon/evening. This supposedly helps focus, and prevents burnout. He also suggests structuring your weeks like this too, although with such a short amount
of time left, not sure I can afford to take any days off…</p>

<p>At any rate, here’s to a good show! I’ll try a post-game analysis to see how well everything worked for me. I’m also planning a post about an idea I’ve been toying with
on how to integrate both tablet and computer for enhanced note taking, à la personal study wikis/the textbook method.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[EZProxify - UMD libraries proxy for reading articles at home]]></title>
    <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2013/01/ezproxify-umd-libraries-proxy-for-reading-articles-at-home/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-03T23:26:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2013/01/ezproxify-umd-libraries-proxy-for-reading-articles-at-home</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here’s a cool little bookmarklet you can use to access journal articles while outside of the UMD IP address block:</p>

<p><a href="javascript:void(location.href='http://proxy-um.researchport.umd.edu/login?url='+location.href)">EZProxify</a></p>

<p>Just drag that link to your address bar, and you’re set to go! 
If you find an article you want to read from home, just click the bookmarklet
and you’ll be routed through the UMD libraries proxy server.</p>

<p>[<a href="http://lib.guides.umd.edu/content.php?pid=233784&amp;sid=1934195">UMD libraries reference page</a>]</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing the (official) launch of PsiQED]]></title>
    <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2012/07/announcing-the-official-launch-of-psiqed/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-02T11:13:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2012/07/announcing-the-official-launch-of-psiqed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The title pretty much says it all – I’m finally launching a blog as I segue
into the graduate lifestyle and start <a href="http://umdphysics.umd.edu/">PhD School</a> in August.</p>

<p>I plan to post on a variety of topics (the only real criterion being things that
interests me), but posts will likely cluster around physics, education, 
technology, and the occasional (software) hack. I also plan to write 
<a href="http://blog.learnstream.org/2012/01/weekly-review-through-december-19/">weekly reviews</a> 
to summarize and collect my thoughts on the week, however interesting or mundane they might be.</p>

<p>That’s about it; stay tuned and check back. We’ll see if I can actually keep this up.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
