<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Education | PsiQED]]></title>
  <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/blog/categories/education/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-05T15:15:47-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://npisenti.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Neal Pisenti]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Where are the subversive narratives in education?]]></title>
    <link href="http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2013/05/where-are-the-subversive-narratives-in-education/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-05T13:03:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://npisenti.github.com/blog/2013/05/where-are-the-subversive-narratives-in-education</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>So what are the narratives we hear about “disruptive innovation” — or even just
innovation — in education? They include things like “education is broken.” The
incumbent players in the sector — teachers, schools, professors, universities,
textbook publishers, and pencil manufacturers — are largely “resistant to
change.” Someone from the outside — and this is key to this narrative — will
provide the disruptive innovation that upsets, dare we say “revolutionizes” the
entire sector. Technology — here’s another key piece of the dominant narrative
— technology has changed, will change everything. Education is broken;
technology will fix it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>(Audrey Watters’ <a href="http://www.hackeducation.com/2013/05/04/ed-tech-argo-f-k-yourself/">keynote address</a> at the <a href="http://edinnovation.ca/">Ed-Tech Innovation Conference</a>).</p>

<p>I’m really glad there are a few voices (like Audrey’s) pushing back against 
many of these ideas in “education reform” which go almost unquestioned nowadays.
Of course, public discourse is (almost by definition) shaped by the
quote-unquote “dominant narrative,” but this happens to the detriment of real
change. It’s easy to see examples of this unfolding in almost every area of
civic life (e.g., “The War on <script type="math/tex">x</script>”, <script type="math/tex">\forall x \in \{ \text{`terror'}, \text{`drugs'}, \ldots \}</script>),
where there is rarely any nuanced discussion of the issues. The situation is even worse for so-called “slow-motion
crises” – like the fact that <a href="http://www.publicintegrity.org/2012/03/27/8536/childrens-defense-fund-report-kids-gun-deaths-new-gun-laws">almost twice as many preschool-aged children die from gunfire than police officers who are killed in the line of duty</a>
– but sensible gun reform measures supported by almost 90% of the country and a
majority of lawmakers die in congress because our society simply cannot manage
to have a nuanced conversation about the issues.</p>

<p>Education inequity, I’d argue, is a slow-moving crisis that only gets discussed in the context of flashy <del>“get rich quick”</del> quick-fix
schemes.  In reality, the problem is always more complex. But by focusing so
heavily on “reform” efforts like (for example) the Khan Academy, we never get to
discuss the deeper structural issues that led to the inequities in the first
place. Why aren’t students in north Baltimore receiving the same quality of
education their peers receive in the rich suburbs of DC? Here’s a hint: it has
very little to do with the quality of the teachers, and will not be remedied by
access to technology that can “flip the classroom.” These are the subversive
narratives we need to hear more about.</p>

<p>Subversive ideas can be uncomfortable, and nuance can be hard. But the
alternative is a system (indeed, our current system) which is so horribly broken
in many respects that I can’t imagine how a status-quo this shitty could arise
except by (slow-moving) apathy or malicious design.</p>

<p>Here is one easy example to get started:</p>

<p>In Baltimore, one dominant narrative is “teacher accountability,” where
“accountability” is achieved by measuring student performance on standardized
tests.</p>

<p>Exhibit A: this year, the curriculum in some Baltimore schools is aligned to the
new Common Core standards, but the state-mandated assessments are still aligned
to the old standards which test an entirely different set of benchmarks.
Teachers following the district-mandated Common Core curriculum (with its
increased emphasis on higher-order thinking) are held accountable for their
students’ performance on skills they aren’t responsible for teaching. </p>

<p>The real result? Hyper-focus on last-minute drilling for the test. The students
lose, the teachers lose, and the rest of the community certainly doesn’t
benefit.  Accountability is not a bad thing; but when it is pursued entirely in
black and white, nobody wins except the politicians who claim they are
“addressing the problem.” </p>

<p>Without nuance, nothing will change. Engaging subversive narratives can draw
nuance into the conversation.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
